David Emmert Brumbaugh Papers
David Emmert Brumbaugh Papers
1939-1962
Brumbaugh, David Emmert (1894-1977)
13 linear ft.
United States congressman from Pennsylvania. Collection includes campaign and election material, correspondence, texts of speeches and bills; also some later material (correspondence and other items) relating to Brumbaugh's tenure as Pennsylvania's Secretary of Banking.
2764890
Biographical History
David Emmert Brumbaugh (1894-1977) was an American banker, insurance executive and legislator. He served in the U.S. Army during World War I, and later was a U.S. Representative from Pennsylvania (1943-1947) and a member of the Pennsylvania state senate (1963-1967). In 1947 Pennsylvania Governor James A. Duff appointed him the state's Secretary of Banking, a position he held until 1952. He was a Pennsylvania delegate to the Republican National Convention in 1952, 1956 and 1960.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The David Emmert Brumbaugh Papers contain three types of material. Because the material is in original order, this material is scattered throughout the collection. The researcher is advised to review the entire inventory carefully to ensure locating all relevant material.
Campaigns and elections material consists of campaign receipts and expenditures, county and town lists of voter registrations, lists of Republican committeemen, candidate's petitions, press releases, election results, and congratulatory messages from constituents.
Material relating to the 78th and 79th Congresses includes the correspondence of Brumbaugh's predecessor, James E. Van Zandt. Much of this correspondence points up the legislative responsibilities of a congressman during World War II and its aftermath. There are letters from constituents requesting help in obtaining passports, sugar, farm deferments, and military discharges. Also included is correspondence relating to the mustering-out pay bill for members of the armed forces, the soldier vote bill, the Continuation of Commodity Credit Corporation with Anti-Food Subsidy provision, the overriding of the President's veto tax bill, extension of the land-lease act, the G.I. Bill of Rights, Townsend Legislation, and more.
Also included in this series are texts of Brumbaugh's speeches before Congress.
Banking-related material covers Brumbaugh's career as Pennsylvania's Secretary of Banking and his correspondence with fellow bankers and banking association officers.
Correspondents of note in the collection include Pennsylvania Governors James A. Duff and Edward Martin, House Minority Leader Joseph W. Martin, Jr., Chester Bowles and Paul Porter.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection has received minimal processing and remains in original order with (for the most part) the donor's original subject headings.
Subject and Genre Headings
Politics, government and public administration; Brumbaugh, David Emmert (1894-1977); Van Zandt, James E. (James Edward), 1898-; Bankers -- Pennsylvania.; Legislators -- Pennsylvania.; Legislators -- United States.; Pennsylvania -- Politics and government -- 1951-; Bills (legislative records); Correspondence.; Photographs.; Speeches (documents); Bankers.; Legislators.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of James Emmert Brumbaugh, circa 1965.
Inventory
- Papers
  - Correspondence
    - A-Boh, 1944-1945 (Box 1)
    - Boj-Co, 1944-1945 (Box 2)
    - Cr-Ey, 1944-1945 (Box 3)
    - Fa-Gw, 1944-1945 (Box 4)
    - Ha-J, 1944-1945 (Box 5)
    - Ka-Mc, 1944-1945 (Box 6)
    - Mc-My, 1944-1945 (Box 7)
    - Na-Q, 1944-1945 (Box 8)
    - Ra-Shop, 1944-1945 (Box 9)
    - Shope-Sw, 1944-1945 (Box 10)
    - Ta-Wa, 1944-1945 (Box 11)
    - We-Z, 1944-1945 (Box 12)
    - Annapolis/West Point, 1946 (Box 13)
    - Army/Navy game tickets, 1946 (Box 13)
    - Applications to West Point, 1946 (Box 13)
    - Case Bill, 1946 (Box 13)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Bills introduced by DEB, 1946 (Box 13)
    - Baby books, 1946 (Box 13)
    - Newspaper articles, 1945-1946 (Box 14)
  - Correspondence
    - A-Cu, 1946 (Box 15)
    - Da-Gu, 1946 (Box 16)
    - Ha-Ly, 1946 (Box 17)
    - Mc-Q, 1946 (Box 18)
    - Ra-Sw, 1946 (Box 19)
    - T-Z, 1946 (Box 20)
    - A-H (O.D.)*, 1946 (Box 20)
    - J-Z (O.D.)*, 1946 (Box 20)
    - James Van Zandt, 1939-1943 (Box 21)
    - Campaign, 1944; 1946 (Box 21)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Election expenditures, 1944 (Box 21)
    - Election receipts and expenditures, 1943 (Box 21)
    - Petitions, 1944 (Box 21)
    - Announcements, 1944 (Box 21)
  - Correspondence
    - Red Cross, 1944; 1945 (Box 22)
    - Sugar, 1946 (Box 22)
    - Sugar shortage, 1946 (Box 22)
    - Sympathy, 1946 (Box 22)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Speeches, 1945-1946 (Box 22)
  - Correspondence
    - Townsend Bill, 1946 (Box 23)
    - Terminal Leave Pay, 1946 (Box 23)
    - U.S. Military Academy, 1941; 1944 (Box 23)
    - U.S. Naval Academy, 1944 (Box 23)
    - Veterans Hospital, 1946 (Box 23)
    - Veterans Hospital, 79th Congress, 1945 (Box 23)
    - HR 309, introduced by DEB, 1945 (Box 23)
    - U.S. Merchant Marine Academy, 1945 (Box 23)
    - Voting record, 1943 (Box 23)
    - HR 1964, 1945 (Box 23)
    - HR 5293, introduced by DEB, 1945 (Box 23)
    - Wedding, 1943 (Box 24)
    - Election results, 1943 (Box 24)
    - Election results, Nov., 1944 (Box 24)
    - 23rd District committeemen and women, 1944 (Box 24)
    - Congratulations, 1944 (Box 24)
    - Birthday, 1944 (Box 24)
    - Compulsory military training (pro and con), 1946 (Box 24)
    - Invitations, 1946 (Box 24)
    - Congratulations, 1946 (Box 24)
    - Coal, 1946 (Box 24)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Congratulations political workers, 1945 (Box 24)
    - Immigrations visa I-133, 1945 (Box 24)
  - Correspondence
    - National Service Law HR 3944, 1944 (Box 25)
    - Omnibus Bill of Legions: HR 3917, HR 4057, S 1767, 1944 (Box 25)
    - Nurse Draft bill, 1945 (Box 25)
    - Lumber, 1946 (Box 25)
    - Lakemont Legion, 1946 (Box 25)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Lists, 1945 (Box 25)
    - Labor drafts, 1945 (Box 25)
    - Nurse Draft bill, 1945 (Box 25)
    - Lake Erie / Ohio River Canal, 1945 (Box 25)
    - Political, 1944 (Box 25)
    - Publicity, 1946 (Box 25)
  - Correspondence
    - [General], 27 Feb 1951-6 Nov 1962 (Box 26)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Speeches (Box 26)
  - Correspondence
    - Post office, 1945 (Box 27)
    - Personal, 1945 (Box 27)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Petitions, 1946 (Box 27)
    - Petitions for primary, 1944 (Box 27)
    - Publicity, 1944 (Box 27)